Guide to the William Bayard Hale Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Bayard Hale papers
1888-1962
MS 814
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.25
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, memorabilia, scrapbooks and printed matter chiefly concentrated in the years 1910-1923. The correspondence includes photocopies of thirteen letters from Woodrow Wilson to Hale (1911-1915) discussing various aspects of United States foreign policy. Between 1913 and 1914, Hale travelled in Central America as Woodrow Wilson's special emissary to Mexico and then to Nicaragua. His letters to his wife during this period describe the political upheavals in those countries and his opposition to United States recognition of the Huerta government in Mexico. Also of note are three letters from Sigmund Freud in which Freud discusses the proper use of psychoanalysis in connection with Hale's just published study of Woodrow Wilson. Other important correspondents include William Jennings Bryan, John Burroughs, Thomas Hardy, Oliver Wendell Holmes, William Dean Howells, H. L. Mencken, Theodore Roosevelt and George Bernard Shaw. There is only a small sampling of his writing and one sermon. The largest part of the collection is made up of scrapbooks and printed matter (1914-1923), reflecting Hale's position during World War I as a secret agent of the Germans. Included are pro-German periodicals and pamphlets published before the United States entry into the war and post war pamphlets on the question of German war guilt and the Versailles Treaty.
Hale, William Bayard, 1869-1924
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William Harlon Hale, 1975. Gift of Susan Hale-de Seve, 2009.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and one addition: I. Personal Papers. II. Printed Matter.
Scope and Contents
The William Bayard Hale Papers, 1888-1939, consist of correspondence, writings, memorabilia, scrapbooks and printed matter written or collected by Hale. The bulk of the material spans the years 1910-1923. Of particular interest are Hale's letters to his wife, which chronicle his career as President Woodrow Wilson's special emissary to Mexico in 1913, and Hale's extensive collection of printed matter relating to World War I.
Series I, PERSONAL PAPERS, begins with Letters of William Bayard Hale to Olga Unger Hale (1910-1921) discussing mainly routine meetings with local and state officials during his stay in Mexico and throughout his travels in Latin America and Europe as a journalist. Hale does, however, write to his wife of the political upheavals in Mexico and Nicaragua in 1913 and 1914 and also of his opposition to United States recognition of the Huerta government in Mexico.
Letters to William Bayard Hale consist of photocopies of letters which William Harlan Hale sold to private collectors in 1971. Included are thirteen letters from Woodrow Wilson to Hale dating from February 10, 1911, to July 12, 1915. Hale was Wilson's confidant until differences over United States policies early in World War I ended their friendship. In his letter of April 2, 1915, Wilson calls Hale's proposal for a United States embargo on arms shipments to belligerent powers "a suggestion of reprisal, and I should be very loath to see this nation...in retaliation of anything proposed on the other side of the water. I really think we should cultivate a different spirit in the matter. We are detached and we can keep our minds clear of any sort of feeling that might mislead us."
Other letters to Hale include three from Sigmund Freud (1922 Jan), in which Freud discusses his ideas on the proper use of psychoanalysis, with particular reference to Hale's newly published book The Story of a Style: A Psychoanalytic Study of Wilson. H.L. Mencken also writes of Hale's book, 1919 Aug 20, "You have invented a new form of criticism... The plain people buried Woodrow. You have erected his imperishable tombstone." Other correspondents of note include William Jennings Bryan, John Burroughs, Thomas Hardy, Oliver Wendell Holmes, William Dean Howells, B.W. Huebsch, Theodore Roosevelt and George Bernard Shaw.
Series I also contains a small amount of Hale's writings, including an early sermon (1895), his address on "The Making of the American Constitution" delivered at Oxford in 1895, arguments against British activities on the seas and the exportation of munitions (1915), and a copy of The Story of a Style.
Finally, Series I includes memorabilia and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings of Hale's articles and of articles about Hale. The scrapbooks cover the years 1908-1923 but also contain an article written in 1934 by Hale's son, William Harlan Hale, and an article which appeared in the New York Times in 1939, in both of which Hale's secret interview with Kaiser Wilhelm in 1908 is discussed.
Series II, PRINTED MATTER, consists of pamphlets and periodicals collected by Hale relating to World War I. Materials included were published both during and after the war. Found here is a sizable collection of pro-German pamphlets and periodicals published in the United States, including The American Monthly, Bull, The Fatherland, New Yorker Bezirks-Nachrichten and Viereck's. Of special interest is material documenting the German response to the Allied occupation after the war, particularly the "shame" caused by the presence of black American troops. Also included here are pamphlets dealing with political prisoners, prisoners of war, German war guilt and the Versailles Treaty.
Biographical / Historical
William Bayard Hale: ordained in 1893; active in politics and writing; turned to journalism in the early 1900s and divested himself of clerical orders in 1909; worked for Cosmopolitan, the World; edited the Philadelphia Public Ledger for four years; worked for the Times and then World's Work; author of numerous books, especially on politics and Woodrow Wilson; from 1914-1918 travelled in Central and South America and acted as a German propagandist.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Treaty of Versailles (1919 June 28); Journalism; Propaganda, American; Propaganda, German; World War, 1914-1918 -- Prisoners and prisons; World War, 1914-1918 -- Propaganda; Costa Rica -- Description and travel; El Salvador -- Description and travel; Guatemala -- Description and travel; Latin America; Mexico -- Description and travel; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- United States; Mexico -- History -- 1910-1946; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1910-1946; Nicaragua -- Description and travel; Nicaragua -- History -- 1909-1937; Panama Canal (Panama); Puerto Rico -- Description and travel; United States -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Venezuela -- Description and travel; Journalists; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925; Burroughs, John, 1837-1921; Carranza, Venustiano, 1859-1920; Chamorro, Emiliano, 1871-; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939; Hale, Olga Unger; Hale, William Bayard, 1869-1924; Hale, William Harlan, 1910-1974; Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, Jr., 1841-1935; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964; Huerta, Victoriano, 1845-1916; Madero, Francisco I., 1873-1913; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Zelaya, José Santos, 1853-1919
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1888-1923, 1934, 1939; Series I; 2' 4" (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE consists of letters from William Bayard Hale to his wife Olga Unger Hale, which are arranged chronologically, and letters to Hale which are arranged alphabetically by writer.
  WRITINGS OF WILLIAM BAYARD HALE is arranged chronologically.
  MEMORABILIA and SCRAPBOOKS
  - Correspondence
    - Letters of William Bayard Hale to Olga Unger Hale, 1910-1912, 1913 February-Nov, 1914, 1916, 1917, 1919, 1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
    - Letters to William Bayard Hale
      - Bryan, William Jennings, 1915 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Burroughs, John, 1908 April 14, June 9 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Freud, Sigmund, 1922 January 3, January 15, January 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Hardy, Thomas, 1909 August 16, October 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1890 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Howells, William Dean, 1900 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Huebsch, B.W., 1922 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Mencken, H.L., 1919 August 30, November 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1904 February 26, 1908 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Shaw, George Bernard, 1909 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Wilson, Woodrow (*), 1911 February 10 - 1915 July 12, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings of William Bayard Hale
    - The Eternal Teacher. A Sermon Preached in the Church of St. Mary-the-Virgin, Oxford on the Eleventh Sunday After Trinity. Oxford: University Press, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Making of the American Constitution. Oxford: University Press, [1895] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Address of Rev. W. Bayard Hale, L.L.D., of Middleboro, Mass., Before the Graduates of St. John's College, Annapolis, Md. June 17, 1896. Annapolis (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "An American View," Germany's Just Cause. New York: The Fatherland, Circa 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Real Issue at Washington," The Case Against Armed Merchantmen [New York press reprint], Circa 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "William Bayard Hale Answers the Tribune," The Vital Issue, No.II, No. 10, 1915 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Rights and British Pretensions on the Seas. New York: Robert M. McBride & Co., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Exportation of Arms and Munitions of War. Should the Government Allow It or Forbid It? The Organization of American Women for Strict Neutrality, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mr. Bayard Hale's Despatches from the West Front to the New York American, and the International News Service. September 1916. Berlin: Deutscher Verlag, Circa 1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Free Speech or Bolshevism?" Viereck's The American Monthly. Vol. X, No. 5, 1919 July (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Story of a Style. New York: B.W. Huebsch, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Memorabilia
    - Aall-Kristiania, Herman Harris. "William Bayard Hale and Woodrow Wilson," Deutsche Rundschau. Jahrgang 48, 1, 1921 October (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Photograph album of William Bayard Hale and family, Circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Maps, passport, photographs, 1909, 1916, 1919, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Re: Theodore Roosevelt, 1910 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook of stories, articles and addresses kept by Minnie Hale, 1888-1896 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Scrapbook re: William Bayard Hale, 1908-1923, 1934, 1939, 1914-1919 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1914-1923; Series II; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  WARTIME and POSTWAR are both arranged alphabetically by country of publication and, following this, alphabetically by topic. Within each category material is arranged chronologically.
  - Wartime
    - British pamphlets, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
    - British pamphlets, 1915, 1916, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - French pamphlets, 1915, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - German pamphlets - German language, Circa 1914, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - German pamphlets - German language - Pictorial works
      - Der Grosse Krieg in Bildern. Nos. 21-25. Berlin: Georg Stilke, 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - German pamphlets - English language, 1914, circa 1914, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - U.S. pamphlets, 1914, circa 1914 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - U.S. pamphlets, 1915, circa 1915, 1916, circa 1916, 1917, circa 1917, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 34-36)
    - U.S. pamphlets: political, 1918, 1919, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Anti-war pamphlets, 1914-1918, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Pamphlets re: political prisoners, 1918, 1919, circa 1919 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Pamphlets re: prisoners of war, 1917, 1918, 1922, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Pro-German pamphlets, 1914, circa 1914, 1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Pro-German periodicals
      - Bull. Vol. 2, No. 8, 1917 October (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - The Fatherland. Vol. IV, Nos. 19-22, Vol. 7, No. 4, 1916 June 14 - July 5, 1917 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 43)
        General
        See also: box 6, folder 43
      - New Yorker Bezirks-Nachrichten. II Jahrgang, No. 12, 1915 April (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Viereck's. Vol. VI, Nos. 10-13, 15, 17-19, 21, Vol. VII, No. 1, 2, 6, 1917 April 11 - December 26 (Box 6, Folder 45)
        See also: box 6, folder 45
  - Postwar
    - British pamphlets, [1919] (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - British periodicals: Foreign Affairs, Vol. II, 1921 April (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - German pamphlets, Circa 1921, 1922, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - German periodicals:
      - Schweizerische Monatshefte für Politik und Kultur. 1. Jahrgang, heft 6, 9, 1921 Sep, 1921 December (Box 6, Folder 49)
      - von Siebert, B. "Einkreisung?" Süddeutsche Monatshefte, 1922 January (Box 6, Folder 49)
      - Stehle, Bruno. "Frankreichs Kriegsvor-bereitung in der Jugend," Süddeutsche Monatshefte, 1922 March (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - U.S. pamphlets, 1919, 1921, circa 1922 (Box 6, Folder 50-51)
    - U.S. pamphlets: pro-German, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - U.S. pamphlets: political, 1919, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - U.S. periodicals: Liberator, Vol. 4, No. 3, 1919, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - U.S. periodicals - Pro-German: The American Monthly. Vol. XIV, Nos. 3-5, Vol. XV, Nos. 5, 7, 1922 May - 1923 September (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Pamphlets and other documents concerning:
      - German response to Allied occupation, 1922, undated (Box 7, Folder 56)
      - German documents on the causes of World War I, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 57)
      - German war guilt, 1920-1923 (Box 7, Folder 58-59)
      - Investigation of the causes of the war:
        - Aall, Herman Harris. The Neutral Investigation of the Causes of Wars. Kristiania, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 60)
        - Bulletin of the Central Commission for Neutral Investigation of the Causes of the World War. Nos. 1, 2/3, 1922 September - 1923 December - January (Box 7, Folder 60)
      - Versailles Treaty, 1919, 1921, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 61)
- Additional material, Accession 2010-M-009
  Includes letters to President Woodrow Wilson and William Jennings Bryan, as well as correspondence not listed in series I of original accession. The proclamation bestowed on W.B. Hale is written in Spanish with an English translation.
  - Correspondence
    - 1907-1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1921-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to President Woodrow Wilson, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to William Jennings Bryan, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clipping, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Summaries of letters and documents owned by Hale, 1904-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proclamation bestowed on W.B.Hale by the President of the United States of Venezuela for outstanding service, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)